Leah: Most young people experience
ups and downs during their childhood
and teenage years and occasionally
will feel down or upset by certain
things going on in their lives.
Rhiannon: Feeling sad or fed up is
a normal reaction to experiences
that are difficult or stressful.
A low mood often involves
sadness, an anxious feeling,
worry and low self-esteem.
It may even involve frustration and anger.
Leah: However, it will tend to improve
after a short time, especially if
the child or young person makes
changes to resolve their problems,
by discussing them, facing them
head on or even getting more sleep.
If children and young people are able
to challenge their negative thoughts
and replace them with positivity, they
are more likely to improve their mood.
Rhiannon: But some young people feel sad,
lonely, down, and anxious or stressed
for much longer periods of time, to
the extent that it can affect their
everyday lives and can prevent them from
doing things they would normally do.
Leah: It is then, when a low mood
doesn’t go away and if anything, gets
worse, that it needs to be looked at
as clinical depression and a mental
condition that needs to be addressed.